Hello. My name is Philippe, and I'm excited to present to you this paper called LMs get lost in
multiturn conversation.
This is in collaboration with my dear friends and colleague, Hiroaki
Hayashi at Salesforce and Jennifer Neville at MSR.
So let me walk you through a little bit of what the motivation of this work is, which is a conversation
Hiro and I had in September 2024,
we were talking about programming language benchmarks
and how they were sort of saturated. Like, if you looked at benchmarks like human eval,
you know, a lot of models were getting 90 plus accuracy on them,
and we felt like, okay, the models at the time were not not very good yet at programming
language tasks.
And
I wasn't sure why I'm not a programming language person, and Hero is an expert on this topic, so we we
kind of, like, looked at some examples together.
And if you're not familiar with human eval, it's an OpenAI dataset,
and it has samples like here on the left where, basically, you're given a docstring of
a function. Here, the example is a function called below zero where you'll be given a list of
deposits with withdrawals
and the bank account that starts with zero, and then your task is to detect if at any point the balance goes below zero
and return true. Otherwise, it should return false. Right? And when you look at this problem, you
might have two intuitions.
The AI intuition is that, you know, okay. Like, the reason why this benchmark is easy is because the task is too simple,
and that real coding tasks are actually, you know, harder than this in terms of complexity.
And then if you're more of an HCI minded person, you might think, oh,
but is this actually how people would write a prompt? Perhaps, like, there's just a misalignment between how this
benchmark is set up and how actual people would use it.
And we started playing around with, you know, okay. How would people actually, you know, wanna implement this function approach
this, you know, if they went to, you know, their favorite chat conversational interface?
And we came up with this idea of a sharded instruction.
The sharded instruction here on the right is an equivalent instruction that has the exact same information as
the instruction here on the left that you can see,
except that it's been split into six shards here.
And each shard essentially is a piece of information
that,
you know, you might reveal in a single turn such that when you simulate a conversation,
you're not gonna reveal all the information needed to do the task at the start, but you might, you know, start by
saying, hey. I need to write a function called below zero that finds if accounts are ever negative. And
then, you know, the model might answer, and then you might say, oh, by the way, the input is a list of ints that represent transaction
amounts.
And then in the third turn, you might say, oh, by the way, we let's assume that the initial balance is zero,
etcetera. And you can kind of see that, like, if you do this, you kind of underspecify
the problem at the start, and you slowly refine the problem, which is realistic because that sometimes users,
you know,
don't know exactly all of what they want as they start the conversation, and they have to refine their intent over time.
So we applied this idea
of, you know, sharding of instructions not only to code problems
based on human eval, but also on other kinds of tasks that people might want might wanna do.
So we did database task and actions around, you know,
tool calling, and then we did math problems, data to text, and summarization.
And these, like, you know, span from programming language to natural language tasks, all generation tasks.
And basically, we took these instructions that exist that are high quality from existing datasets, and then we
implemented the sharding process here shown in yellow.
And from there, we, you know, implemented what we call a simulation
environment that, you know, takes in
a sharded instruction
and can simulate a multi turn conversation
by leveraging a small language model at the time we use GPT four o mini to kind of decide, okay. At
each point in the conversation when the assistant has responded,
we have a little decider that can choose, okay. Which shard should I reveal next? And, essentially, the
idea is to reveal at most one one new chart of information per turn so that the conversations are multi
turn and underspecified.
Alright.
So with this in mind, you know, you might be wondering, okay. Like, I think I know where this is
going. You're gonna tell me that the, you know, sharded multi turn performance in the underspecified setting is gonna
perform worse than the fully specified single turn. And one idea you might have is
maybe this loss is due to the actual sharding process.
When you shard the information in, you know, an instruction into multiple shards, if you're not
careful, you might lose some information during the sharding,
and that might make the task infeasible in the multi turn setting. Right? So we have to be careful about this.
And because of this, we implemented what we call the concat experiment, and let me show you what that looks like.
The idea is we're gonna simulate know, given a fully specified instruction
and its sharded equivalent,
we're gonna have three ways of conducting,
you know, a simulated conversation.
The full conversation is just the we just provide the, you know, single instruction at the start,
the original one, and then let the assistant complete the task.
Sharded is as we said. You know, we're gonna shard the converse the the instruction
and then give one shard per turn. And then concat, the idea is we're
gonna take the shards
of the sharded instructions, put them in a bullet list, and provide all of that information in a single turn.
So now, hopefully, you'll see that, like, the concat versus full, they're both single turn,
and the only difference is the rephrasing that has occurred during sharding.
And then concat versus sharding
sharded, they're exactly the same words, the same paraphrasing,
except the only difference now is single versus multiturn.
So, hopefully, concat is gonna, you know, kind of separate the the the effect from the sharding rephrasing
that has occurred.
This is the main results of the paper, and, hopefully, you can see that, you know, there's the long story short is that
we find that, you know, given the performance here on the left of, you know, one model per row
and on the six tasks that we that we experimented with, you know, we can see that the full
performance and the concat performance are mostly the same. You can see the colors are mostly white. Some of the
older and and smaller models perform a little worse in concat, but the top models that we tested
do pretty good and pretty similarly in full and concat. On the other hand, there's large degradation that
we that we observe when we go into the sharded, you know, underspecified multi return setup.
Okay? And then let me now get into why do models get lost in conversation.
So we actually for each, you know, simulates for each instruction that we have,
we actually ran 10 simulations
instead of one.
And what we're interested in in seeing, you know, not only the average performance, which is what we saw in the table above,
but also two new metrics that we came up with. One is called aptitude, and it corresponds to basically
the best case performance for any given instruction, which is the ninetieth percentile performance,
and also unreliability,
which is the the gap between
best and worst case performance. So the gap between ninetieth and tenth percentile.
And the observation that we have is that, you know, the degradation in performance that we observe
from blue to yellow here
mostly occurs
as a small drop in aptitude, meaning the best case performance drops a little bit, but an
a very large increase in unreliability,
meaning that the worst case and
worst case to best case performance has dropped a lot.
So the way we phrase this is that when LLMs take a wrong turn in a conversation, they get lost and do not recover.
It's not that in multi turn settings, the models become incapable of completing certain tasks.
It's just that there is more room for the models to get things wrong, which means that the unreliability has increased a lot
of the system.
Okay.
Some additional experiments that we conducted.
One is you might be thinking, okay. But what if we implement an agent that has memory and
that can, like, say,
recap the information that has occurred so far in the conversation, would that help reduce the amount
of, you know, information loss and degradation in performance?
So we implemented two new kinds of simulations that you can see here in the diagram. One is called
recap and one is called snowball.
And both of them, essentially, you know, as we introduce new shards of information in the conversation, we also
implement a system to, you know,
repeat the information that has occurred so far in the conversation.
And the finding from our experiment here on the right is what you can see is that, you know, that does improve
performance compared to just plain sharded simulation, but it doesn't quite close the gap. So agents
help a little bit, but they don't fundamentally solve the problem, at least the way we set it up.
Another thing you might be thinking is what about temperature?
Reliability
of AI systems can sometimes be related to temperature because these systems are stochastic.
So we tried reducing the temperature of both the assistant, this is on the columns,
and also the
the user simulator
here in the in the rows.
And we find that in the singleton scenario,
so this is concat in full, blowing temperature does help reduce unreliability.
On the other hand, it has almost no effect in the multi turn setting. And that's because in multi turn
setting, even a small token divergence in an early turn basically cascades and becomes entirely
different conversations.
So we find that decreasing temperature even to zero does not lead to reduced
unreliability in multiturn setups.
We have some additional information
in the paper about what are the reasons that models get lost.
One of them is that the models make answer attempts too early even if they don't have all the elements
of the problem. We find that, you know, the the later that the model makes an attempt,
the better the performance.
We we also find that there is this concept of answer blow that as the model goes deeper and deeper in the
conversation,
the models aren't very good at invalidating bad assumptions, and so their answers sort of tend to bloat.
So even if you get a correct answer at the end of a multi turn conversation, it's bloated by 30 to 40% compared
to single turn.
We also find that there is a loss in middle turns phenomenon where basically
the the models pay more attention to early information or late information but not
middle information.
And that models tend to produce overly verbose answers,
which tends to confuse them later in the conversation because they get confused with prior assumptions that they
made that were incorrect.
That's it. Thanks for listening.
The TLDR is that, you know,
sharding instructions in a is a, you know, seemingly benign way
that leads to catastrophic degradation in LLM performance on both natural language and programming language
generation tasks.
This manifests as a loss of reliability specifically,
and that means that models can still do everything sometimes,
and, of course, this is bad for users. So the what we want you to remember is that when LLMs take a wrong
turn, they get lost and do not recover. Thank you for listening.